So, hello, everyone.
所以，大家好。
So today we are going to finish the discussion on scheduling.
今天我们要完成关于日程安排的讨论。
And then we are going to start the discussion on deadlocks.
然后我们将开始讨论死锁问题。
So last time we discussed quite a bit about a few scheduling disciplines.
上次我们讨论了一些调度策略。
And if you remember one scheduling disciplines, which has been very popular and is still popular,
如果你还记得一个调度策略，它曾经非常流行，而且现在仍然很受欢迎，
it's priority scheduling.
这是优先级调度。
And one of the reason it's popular, it's very simple.
而且它受欢迎的原因之一是非常简单。
The pure priority scheduling, if you remember, you have different levels of priorities and
纯优先级调度，如果你记得的话，你有不同级别的优先级和
you always start from the highest priority and then you run the jobs at the highest priority.
你总是从最高优先级开始，然后按最高优先级运行任务。
And only after you are done with those jobs, you can go to the lower priority.
完成这些工作之后，你才能去做优先级较低的工作。
And one obvious question is does prioritizing some jobs necessarily starve those that aren't
而一个明显的问题是，优先考虑某些工作是否必然会使其他工作陷入困境？
prioritized?
优先考虑的？
So do higher priority jobs necessarily starve lower priority jobs?
高优先级的工作是否一定会使低优先级的工作得不到满足？
And this is what we are going to talk a little bit about here and what kind of tweaks you
而这就是我们将在这里稍微谈一下的内容，以及你想要进行哪些微调。
can do to priority scheduling to avoid starvation.
可以采取优先调度来避免饥饿现象。
Because if you remember, if you have always high priority jobs, then you'll never serve
因为如果你记得的话，如果你总是有高优先级的工作，那么你就永远无法服务。
the low priority jobs.
低优先级的工作。
So therefore, you are going to starve the low priority jobs.
所以，你打算让低优先级的工作饿肚子。
So let's look through some of these mechanisms.
那么让我们来看一下这些机制。
So one mechanism, it's an API which is provided by early Unix systems, which is called Nice.
所以有一个机制，它是早期Unix系统提供的一个API，被称为Nice。
And this, as the name implies, it allows you as a user to be nice to others.
而且，正如其名称所示，它允许你作为用户对他人友善。
And the way you are going to be nice to others is by lowering the priority of your job, of
而你要对他人友善的方式是降低你工作的优先级，以及
your application.
你的申请。
So in this case, in the case of Unix, lower values of priorities mean high priority.
所以在这种情况下，对于Unix来说，优先级较低的值意味着较高的优先级。
And the nice value ranges from minus 20 to 19.
并且优先级的取值范围从负20到19。
So negative values are not nice.
所以负值不好。
And in order to be nice, you can increase this value, which means lower priority.
为了友好起见，你可以增加这个值，这意味着降低优先级。
So that's very interesting.
那真是非常有趣。
So now a few words about Linux.
关于Linux，现在说几句话。
Let's see how Linux, the basic scheduler, it's organized and it's implemented.
让我们来看看Linux的基本调度器是如何组织和实现的。
So you have 140 priorities.
所以你有140个优先事项。
And the first 100 are for the kernel and the real time tasks.
前100个是用于内核和实时任务。
Again, the real time tasks are the ones who are predictable, you want to be predictable.
再次强调，实时任务是那些可预测的任务，你希望能够做到可预测。
And then the last 40 are for the user tasks.
然后最后的40个是用于用户任务。
And again, lower priority values, it means higher priority.
再次，较低的优先级值意味着较高的优先级。
And the algorithm is O(1).
并且该算法的时间复杂度是O(1)。
O(1) complexity meaning that it takes constant time to select the next process to run.
O(1)复杂度意味着选择下一个要运行的进程所需的时间是恒定的。
And you also have time slices, so it's preemptive scheduler.
你也有时间片，所以这是一个抢占式调度器。
So a job or a process doesn't run to completion is going to be interrupted when its time slice
所以，当一个工作或一个进程没有运行到完成时，当它的时间片到期时会被中断。
expires.
过期。
There is also 140 bit mask, which indicates the presence or absence of a job at the given
还有一个140位的掩码，用于指示给定位置是否存在或缺失一个工作。
priority level.
优先级水平。
So why do you have that bit mask?
那么你为什么要使用那个位掩码？
So the reason you have that bit mask is that, think about you want to be very quick and
所以你有那个位掩码的原因是，想想你想要非常快速和
you select the next job or next process to run.
你选择下一个工作或下一个流程来运行。
And now assume that you have two processes in the system, one process at priority zero
然后假设系统中有两个进程，一个进程的优先级为零。
and one process at priority 139.
和一个优先级为139的进程。
So once you're finished to run the process at priority zero, you need to run the process
所以一旦你完成以优先级零运行该进程，你需要运行该进程。
at priority 139.
在优先级139。
But you need to find that process.
但是你需要找到那个过程。
And the simple implementation is to have a list of priorities and each head of that,
而简单的实现方法是拥有一个优先级列表，每个列表都有一个头部，
for each item in this priority list, it's a list of processes at that priority.
对于这个优先级列表中的每个项目，它是该优先级下的一系列进程。
So now you start from zero and you are done with the process.
所以现在你从零开始，你已经完成了整个过程。
And now you have to go to next one, which is the next level and the next level and the
现在你需要去下一个，也就是下一级别和下一级别和下一级别。
next level until you get to 139 in order to find the next process to run.
一直升级直到达到139级，以找到下一个要运行的进程。
If you have a bit mask, then basically the bit mask, I'm just going to look at the bit
如果你有一个位掩码，那么基本上位掩码，我只会看位。
mask, which is 140 bits.
口罩，有140个位。
And the bit mask will say that the next automatic will say that only there are processes active
并且位掩码将指示下一个自动将指示只有活动的进程。
at level priority level 139.
在优先级为139的级别上。
In between, there is no process active.
中间没有进行中的过程。
So the bits in the bit mask are not set.
所以位掩码中的位没有被设置。
So it's very easy to do.
所以这很容易做到。
The other thing which is doing is that you have two priority queues in terms of for active
另一件事情是，你有两个优先队列，用于处理活跃的事务。
processes, the processes which you have to, they are still to run and then expired processes.
进程，你必须处理的进程，它们仍然需要运行，然后是已过期的进程。
Expired means after you are going to run a process, you are going to put it in the expired
过期的意思是在你要运行一个进程之后，你要将其放入过期状态。
queue.
排队。
And then once you are done with all the processes in the active queue, so the active queue is
然后一旦你完成了活动队列中的所有流程，那么活动队列就是
empty, you just switch to expired.
空的，你只是切换到了过期的状态。
So active become expired queue and expired becomes the active queue.
所以活跃队列变成了过期队列，过期队列变成了活跃队列。
You swap them.
你互换它们。
Okay, so this is what an example.
好的，这是一个例子。
You go through the active queues, you have here all these priorities, each task with
你浏览活动队列，这里有所有这些优先级，每个任务都有。
its own priorities.
它自己的优先事项。
And once you are done with all the tasks from the active queue, you are going to put them
而一旦你完成了所有来自活动队列的任务，你将把它们放置在哪里？
all in the expired queue.
所有在过期队列中。
And then you are just going to swap the expired queue with the run queue.
然后你只需要将过期队列与运行队列进行交换。
Any questions?
有任何问题吗？
And then in order to avoid kind of starvation, like we discussed last time, there are many
然后为了避免像我们上次讨论的那种饥饿，有很多方法。
heuristics.
启发式算法。
Like if a task is IO bound, you try to boost this priority, to increase this priority.
如果一个任务是IO绑定的，你会尝试提高它的优先级，增加这个优先级。
If a task running for too long, you are going to lower like his priority.
如果一个任务运行时间太长，你会降低它的优先级。
More precisely, here is a list of heuristics.
更准确地说，这是一份启发式规则的列表。
The user task priority is adjusted in plus minus five increments.
用户任务优先级在加减五个增量内进行调整。
It's again, you have the user task priority is between 100 and 139.
再次提醒，您的用户任务优先级应在100至139之间。
And basically you are going to update it like for instance, if the sleep time minus run
然后基本上你要更新它，比如，如果睡眠时间减去跑步时间。
time, if the process sleeps much longer than it runs, you increase its priority.
如果进程休眠的时间比运行时间长得多，你可以提高它的优先级。
This is probably because it's an IO bound task.
这可能是因为它是一个IO绑定的任务。
If it's running for a long time, you are going to decrease its priority.
如果它运行了很长时间，你要降低它的优先级。
And if it doesn't sleep at all.
而且如果它根本不睡觉。
So yeah, again, if your task sleep for a long time, you are going to accrue credit, you
所以，是的，如果你的任务长时间休眠，你将会积累信用。
are going to increase the priority.
我们将提高优先级。
When it's going to run, you are going to spend this credit, you're going to decrease this
当它开始运行时，你将会使用这个信用，你将会减少它。
priority if it's running for too long.
如果运行时间过长，优先级会降低。
And for interactive tasks, you give them special treatment because you want to always have
而对于互动任务，你给予它们特殊对待，因为你希望始终拥有
high priority.
高优先级。
Although in general, many of the interactive tasks are IO bound because they are waiting
尽管一般来说，许多交互任务是受IO限制的，因为它们需要等待。
for the user input, many of them.
对于用户输入，有很多种。
So then they can go automatically higher priority because they are going to sleep more than
所以他们可以自动提高优先级，因为他们要比其他人睡得更多。
they are.
他们是。
So let's see, there are two questions here.
那么让我们来看看，这里有两个问题。
That's a very good question.
这是一个非常好的问题。
So the question is, does this mean getting a new process scheduled takes a long time
所以问题是，这是否意味着安排一个新的流程需要很长时间？
since the existing queue needs to be exhausted before new things can be added?
因为现有的队列需要被处理完毕才能添加新的事物？
Yeah, you are right.
是的，你说得对。
It's a strategy in the process is getting scheduled, not the process itself.
这是一个正在进行调度的策略，而不是过程本身。
So you are again, when you have one process, one thread, we are going to use interchangeable.
所以你又来了
So this very much depends on the scheduler.
这非常取决于调度程序。
But when you are going to run a new process, typically you put the process as the highest
但是当你要运行一个新的进程时，通常你会将该进程设置为最高优先级。
priority.
优先级。
So this means that you are going to start executing that process or thread quickly,
所以这意味着你将快速开始执行该进程或线程，
which is the highest priority.
哪个是最高优先级。
You can start executing that thread as soon as you finish executing the current thread,
你可以在当前线程执行完毕后立即开始执行那个线程。
when the time slice of the current thread you are executing is expiring.
当你正在执行的当前线程的时间片即将过期时。
It's also here, you see the word of hysteresis.
这里也有，你看到了滞后的这个词。
You use hysteresis to avoid changing interactivity from temporarily changing changes in behavior.
您使用滞后效应来避免由于行为的暂时变化而导致交互性的变化。
What is hysteresis?
滞后是指系统在受到外部影响后，其响应速度比外部影响的变化速度慢的现象。
Do you know?
你知道吗？
Anyone you can say on the chat?
你可以在聊天中说任何人吗？
Okay, we are not going to go into a lot of details here, but hysteresis means that when
好的，我们这里不会详细讨论，但滞后效应意味着当...
you have a process, a control system in general, and you have a threshold, and when that exceeds
你有一个流程，一个通常的控制系统，还有一个阈值，当超过这个阈值时
that threshold, you change the output and you decrease the threshold, you reduce the
那个阈值，你改变输出并降低阈值，你减少了
gain change output.
增益变化输出。
So if you have a system which is just around that threshold, the system changes its behavior
所以如果你有一个接近这个阈值的系统，系统会改变其行为。
quite frequently.
相当频繁。
So you get one, two, and even if you have noise, if you have to imagine that you have
所以你得到一个，两个，甚至如果有噪音，如果你不得不想象你有
noise around that threshold.
噪音超过了那个阈值。
So you want to avoid that.
所以你想要避免那个。
So in order to avoid that, you have actually in general two thresholds.
所以为了避免这种情况，你实际上一般有两个阈值。
You have one threshold, low threshold and high thresholds.
你有一个门槛，低门槛和高门槛。
And you change the behavior when you exceed a high threshold or when you go under the
并且当您超过一个高阈值或者当您低于一个阈值时，您会改变行为。
low threshold.
低门槛。
So in that sense, you have a range in which the system behavior doesn't change it.
那么从这个意义上说，你有一个范围，在这个范围内系统的行为不会改变。
So if there is a noise and we are within that range, the system will become constant.
所以如果有噪音并且我们在那个范围内，系统将保持稳定。
So for instance, in this particular case, you don't want to change the behavior.
所以例如，在这种特定情况下，你不想改变行为。
Like for instance, imagine that you have an editor.
比如说，想象一下你有一个编辑器。
And with an editor, not editor, maybe, I don't know whether you use LaTeX or something like
而且使用一个编辑器，不是编辑者，也许不是，我不知道你是否使用LaTeX或类似的东西。
that.
那个。
So you have an editor.
所以你有一个编辑器。
Okay, let's take an editor.
好的，让我们来找一个编辑。
So you take an editor and there are two different regimes.
所以你需要一个编辑器，有两种不同的制度。
One you are entering the text, editing the text.
一旦你输入了文本，就可以编辑文本了。
And another one is for instance, you save or load.
另一个例子是，比如说，你可以保存或加载。
So you don't want, say save or load or even worse, the editor doing some rendering and
所以你不想要，比如保存或加载，甚至更糟的是，编辑器进行一些渲染和处理。
doing some compute heavy, say maybe operations.
进行一些计算密集型的工作，比如可能是一些操作。
You don't want that just because you do a little bit of computation, that to make the
你不想要那个只是因为你做了一点点计算，就认为可以实现。
editor less responsive.
编辑反应较慢。
You want to be more robust and only if it's for a long, long time, the editor is just
你想要更加强大，只有在很长很长的时间里才能实现，编辑只是一个工具。
doing a lot of rendering, maybe you are going to deprioritize it.
做了很多渲染，也许你要将其降低优先级。
That's what hysteresis means.
这就是滞后效应的意思。
Real-time tasks, they have lower than 100 priority.
实时任务，它们的优先级低于100。
They also preempt the non-RTH task.
他们还抢占了非RTH任务。
For each queue at each level, there are two kinds of schemes.
对于每个级别的每个队列，有两种方案。
So at each priority level, again, you have multiple, at each priority level, you have
所以在每个优先级别上，再次，你有多个，在每个优先级别上，你有
a queue which contains multiple processes or threads.
一个包含多个进程或线程的队列。
And you can use all the FIFO without no time slice or round-robin, in which there is a
而且你可以使用所有的先进先出（FIFO）算法，无需时间片或轮转，其中包含一个
time slice.
时间片。
Here is a real-time task.
这是一个实时任务。
They are not scheduled using the early deadline first, which we learned last time, the last
他们没有按照我们上次学到的先使用早期截止日期的方式进行安排，而是按照最后期限进行安排。
lecture.
讲座。
They are assigned priorities.
它们被分配了优先级。
There are other scheduling algorithms, real-time scheduling algorithms, which can use priorities
有其他调度算法，实时调度算法，可以使用优先级。
to schedule these tasks and still guarantees you can meet the deadlines.
安排这些任务并确保你能按时完成。
Another thing, like if you remember, we can do and to be more robust and avoid starvation,
另外一件事，就像你记得的那样，我们可以做一些改进，使系统更加稳健，避免饥饿现象。
is basically using proportional share scheduling.
基本上使用的是比例共享调度。
And this is related with lottery scheduling.
这与抽奖调度有关。
lottery scheduling is an implementation of proportional share scheduling.
抽奖调度是比例份额调度的一种实现方式。
And basically here, it's again, if you remember, you allocate these tickets and you have say
而基本上，在这里，如果你还记得的话，你分配这些票，然后你有说
100 tickets, and maybe you are going to give to one thread, you are going to give 10 tickets
100张票，也许你会给一个帖子，你会给10张票。
and the other 190 tickets.
和其他190张票。
And now you are going to do the lottery so every time you select a winning ticket.
现在你要进行彩票抽奖，每次都会选出一张中奖票。
Now obviously, the probability of selecting the second thread, which has 90 tickets, is
现在显然，选择第二个线程的概率是90张票。
nine times higher than probably to select the first thread, which has only 10 tickets.
比起只有10张票的第一条线程，选择可能性高出九倍。
So this means that you give to the second thread 90% of the CPU on the average, and
这意味着你平均给第二个线程90%的CPU使用率，而且
the first thread only 10%.
第一个线程只有10%。
So you can see that you can use this kind of weights, these different number of tickets,
所以你可以看到，你可以使用这种类型的权重，这些不同数量的票。
you are giving to each thread to approximate priorities.
你正在为每个线程分配近似的优先级。
Because clearly, you can see that the thread with 90 tickets has a higher priority than
因为显然，你可以看到拥有90张票的帖子比拥有10张票的帖子优先级更高。
the task with 10 tickets.
任务有10张票。
And the nice thing about this kind of scheme is that it avoids starvation.
而这种方案的好处是它避免了饥饿。
So even if you give a task, a thread 99 tickets and another thread only one, still out on
所以即使你给一个线程99个任务，而另一个线程只有一个任务，结果还是会超时。
the average, out of 100 time slices or quanta, the thread which has only one ticket is going
平均而言，在100个时间片或量子中，只有一张票的线程正在进行。
to get a chance to run.
获得一个机会去奔跑。
So it's not stopped.
所以它没有停止。
And this is basically tells you a little bit more, giving you a little bit more math on
这基本上告诉你更多一点，给你更多的数学上的东西。
that.
那个。
Now, you may ask, well, then why we don't do only this lottery scheduling or this proportional
现在，你可能会问，那么为什么我们不只做这个抽奖调度或这个比例调度呢？
sharing?
分享？
The answer is that it's harder to implement.
答案是实施起来更困难。
It's more complex to implement.
这个实施起来更加复杂。
It's slower than the priority.
比优先级慢。
The priority or so is so on of one super simple to implement.
优先级或者说是如此如此的一个超级简单的实现。
So that's the answer.
这就是答案。
So look, let's again, Unix has a lot of schedulers, actually.
所以看，让我们再说一遍，Unix实际上有很多调度器。
The first one was a basic scheduler.
第一个是一个基本的调度程序。
You have this kind of two queues, active and expired.
你有这样两个队列，一个是活动队列，一个是过期队列。
And it's all fun, very simple.
而且这一切都很有趣，非常简单。
But it has also a more sophisticated scheduler.
但它还有一个更复杂的调度程序。
And one of that, this is completely fair scheduler.
其中之一，这是一个完全公平的调度器。
And the idea here is to track the CPU time per thread and schedule threads to match up
这里的想法是跟踪每个线程的CPU时间，并安排线程以匹配。
on average rate of execution.
平均执行速度。
So basically, in other words, you want different threads.
所以基本上，换句话说，你想要不同的线程。
If you don't have different threads, more than one thread, you want all of them to make
如果你没有不同的线程，只有一个线程，你希望它们都执行。
kind of progress at the same rate.
进展的速度有点相同。
That's it.
就这样。
That's a high level.
这是一个高水平。
So this is if the CPU time, like this is CPU time and this is one over n, you have three
这是CPU时间，这是一个除以n的数，你有三个。
threads.
线程。
So in this case, n is three.
所以在这种情况下，n是三。
So this is each of them, you get one third of the CPU.
所以这是每个人，你得到CPU的三分之一。
Then you look at how long each of them they run, starting for a given time.
然后你看看它们每个人跑了多久，从给定的时间开始。
And in this case, the one that are longer than T2 and T3.
在这种情况下，指的是比T2和T3更长的那些。
And therefore, here you are going to give the next time when you are going to schedule,
所以，你打算在下次安排时给出时间。
you are going to schedule.
你要安排日程。
select probability two, because you want to catch up with,
选择概率二，因为你想迎头赶上。
T2 to catch up with T1 and T3.
T2需要赶上T1和T3。
Of course, it's again, this is a simple one,
当然，这又是一个简单的。
a simple case, but it's sort of complicated, right?
一个简单的案例，但是有点复杂，对吗？
Because threads do not start at the same time.
因为线程不会同时开始。
Threads, excuse me, threads are IO bounded, right?
是的，线程，对不起，线程是受IO限制的，对吗？
They instead of, you know,
他们代替，你知道的，
they don't use their entire full quanta, okay?
他们没有使用他们全部的量子，好吗？
So there are many things and that's why these schedulers
所以有很多事情，这就是为什么这些调度程序。
are much more complicated.
非常复杂。
There are a lot of papers, research papers,
有很多论文，研究论文，
written about the schedulers.
关于调度程序的写作。
This is discussion is to give you a sense,
这次讨论是为了让你有一个感觉，
some intuition about what are the problems
一些关于问题是什么的直觉
and how these schedulers are working, okay?
这些调度器是如何工作的，好吗？
So this is, it's again, this is a goal here
这是一个目标。
is to provide this illusion of complete, of fairness.
是为了提供这种完整、公平的幻觉。
Each of the tasks thread gets the same kind of,
每个任务线程都得到相同类型的。
makes progress at the same rate, gets CPU at the same rate.
以相同的速度取得进展，以相同的速度获取CPU。
And it's closely related to its fair queuing, okay?
而且它与公平排队密切相关，好吗？
How do you implement it?
你如何实施它？
You can use a heap scheduler, but it's hard.
你可以使用堆调度器，但是很难。
A heap scheduler is log N, right?
堆调度器的时间复杂度是log N，对吗？
Or N is a number of threads.
或者N是线程的数量。
And if you look about the number of threads on your Mac
并且如果你查看你的Mac上的线程数量
or on your probably PC, you'll see that you can have
或者在你的电脑上，你会发现你可以拥有
on your machine, you can have like tens of thousands
在你的机器上，你可以拥有成千上万个。
of threads at a given time, tens of thousands.
同时有成千上万个线程。
So this is, can be quite slow, the log N.
这是一个相对较慢的算法，时间复杂度为O(log N)。
Hard to remove threads, right?
很难去除线程，对吗？
Right, but this is a very easy, you know,
没错，但这很简单，你知道的。
using a heap like scheduling, it's easy because you are,
使用堆调度算法很容易，因为你是的。
you can always from a heap, you are going to get,
你可以随时从一堆中得到你想要的东西。
select the task, which has a lowest CPU time,
选择具有最低CPU时间的任务。
which use a CPU as a list, okay?
使用一个CPU作为列表，可以吗？
Now, we said that these things are more complicated.
现在，我们说这些事情更加复杂。
You can have a sleeping, you know, threads.
你可以睡觉，知道吗，线程。
What do you do if a thread is slipping?
如果线头滑动，你会怎么做？
Because, you know, waits for some event to happen,
因为，你知道的，等待某个事件发生，
or, you know, it's like, think about the thread is slipping,
或者，你知道的，就像是，想象一下线程滑动的感觉，
which as a process, when forks, another process
其中一个进程在分叉时，会生成另一个进程。
is going to slip and to wait for the other process
将要滑倒并等待其他过程。
to finish and to join back.
完成并重新加入。
So basically one thing to hear is like when you,
所以基本上一个要听的事情就是当你，
when a thread slips, you don't add basic CPU types.
当线程滑动时，您不需要添加基本的CPU类型。
If you don't advance your CPU time, then when it wakes up,
如果您不提前设置CPU时间，那么当它唤醒时，
it's going to have low CPU time,
它将具有较低的CPU时间。
so it's going to have priority,
所以它将具有优先权，
it's going to be scheduled, right?
会安排的，对吗？
But now the problem is that you cannot do that unbounded.
但是现在的问题是你不能无限制地这样做。
Like what happens if I have a thread,
如果我有一个线程，会发生什么？
which is slips from here since yesterday, right?
你是说从昨天开始滑倒的那个吗？
That will have a higher than, a lower CPU times
那将会有比较高的CPU时间，比较低的CPU时间
than anything in the system.
比系统中的任何东西都重要。
And basically, you know,
基本上，你知道的，
it's going to have priority over all of them.
它将优先于所有其他事物。
So you need to adjust for that as well.
所以你也需要进行调整。
It's again, we are not going to go into all the details.
再说一次，我们不打算深入讨论所有的细节。
So, but at the high level, one trade off with the schedulers,
所以，但在高层次上，调度器的一个权衡是，
like we also discussed last lecture,
就像我们在上一堂课上讨论的那样，
it's about between being very responsive
这是关于非常响应的问题。
and between, within responsibility and fairness.
以及责任和公平之间。
Right? You remember, it's like an algorithm,
对吧？你记得，就像一个算法，
which is fair, it's round robin, right?
是的，这是公平的，这是循环赛制，对吗？
Each of them, you know, you go over, you know,
他们每个人，你知道的，你过去，你知道的。
around the threads and every round you are going to schedule
在每一轮中，你都要安排好各个线程。
to give a time quanta to each thread, right?
给每个线程分配一个时间量子，对吗？
So that's very fair.
这样很公平。
However, maybe don't be very responsive
然而，也许不要太积极回应。
because you have any threads,
因为你有任何线程，
you need to wait for N minus up to N minus one times quanta.
你需要等待N减去一直到N减去一次的量子时间。
To get a time quanta to a thread, right?
获取一个时间片给线程，对吗？
So thread, particular thread can wait
所以线程，特定的线程可以等待。
for N minus one times quanta.
对于N减一次量子。
On the other hand, the priority, it's very effective
另一方面，优先级很高，非常有效。
and provide you low response time,
并且能够提供您低延迟的响应时间，
at least for the threads with a high priority, right?
至少对于优先级较高的线程，是吗？
If you have, say 10 threads
如果你有10个线程的话
and the interactive thread is priority,
而且交互式线程是优先的。
the highest priority, that is going to serve very fast,
最高优先级，即将提供非常快速的服务。
but it's not going to be fair, right?
但这不会公平，对吧？
Because the high priority threads are going to get
因为高优先级的线程将会得到
all the CPU at the expense of low priority threads.
牺牲低优先级线程的情况下，占用所有的CPU资源。
Right? So that's a fundamental trade-off.
对吗？所以这是一个基本的权衡。
And what Linux is doing, it has this kind of,
而Linux正在做的是，它具有这种类型的功能，
you have put this constraint about target latency.
你对目标延迟设置了这个限制。
So it's a period of time over which
所以这是一个时间段，持续一段时间。
every process gets serviced, right?
每个过程都会得到服务，对吗？
I am guaranteed that, you know, target latency.
我保证，你知道目标延迟。
So say it is 100 milliseconds,
所以说它是100毫秒。
I am guaranteed that I'm going to get access to the CPU
我保证我将获得访问CPU的权限。
within every 100 milliseconds.
每100毫秒内。
Okay?
好的。
And this defines a time quanta,
这定义了一个时间量子。
because if you have N number is a number of processes
因为如果你有N个数字，那就是一组进程的数量。
or thread, then the time quanta
或者线程，然后是时间量子。
is a target latency over N, right?
是指超过N的目标延迟，对吗？
So for instance, if you have the target latency,
那么举个例子，如果你有目标延迟时间，
20 milliseconds, and you have four processes,
20毫秒，你有四个进程。
but it's a time quanta, it has to be five, right?
但这是一个时间量子，它必须是五，对吗？
Because if it's longer, you cannot guarantee
因为如果时间更长，你无法保证
that each process is going to get access to the CPU
每个进程都将获得对CPU的访问权限。
within 20 milliseconds.
20毫秒内。
Right?
对吗？
But now if you have 20 milliseconds,
但是现在如果你有20毫秒的时间，
and you have 200 processes,
你有200个进程。
the time quanta can be 0.1 milliseconds,
时间量子可以是0.1毫秒。
which is too little, right?
这太少了，对吗？
You remember, if it's a time slice
你记得，如果是时间片段的话
or time quanta is too small,
或者时间量子太小，
then the overhead of context switching can dominate.
那么上下文切换的开销可能会占主导地位。
So you are doing more context switches
所以你正在进行更多的上下文切换。
between these kinds of processes
这些过程之间
than really running these processes.
比起真正运行这些进程。
Right?
对吗？
So this is one thing.
这是一件事情。
The other thing is about,
另外一件事是关于...
obviously, the reason you want to avoid
显然，你想要避免的原因是什么？
a lot of overhead in context switching
上下文切换中有很多开销。
is to preserve the throughput, right?
是为了保持吞吐量，对吗？
The throughput is defined as a useful work done by a system.
吞吐量被定义为系统所完成的有用工作量。
Context switching is not useful work, okay?
上下文切换并不是有用的工作，好吗？
And therefore, in order to make sure
因此，为了确保
that the throughput is not going to plummet,
吞吐量不会暴跌，
it's not going to be too low,
这不会太低，
you are going to, we are going to say,
你要说的话是什么？
what is the minimum length of any time slice?
任何时间片的最小长度是多少？
So it's a minimum granularity constraints.
所以这是一个最小粒度的约束。
So you have a target latency and minimum granularity,
所以你有一个目标延迟和最小粒度，
which in general can be at odds, right?
一般来说，它们可能存在分歧，对吗？
So,
所以，
so, but, and because they are at odds in,
所以，但是，而且因为他们在不同的立场上。
sometimes you have to violate one.
有时候你必须违背一个。
Like for instance, if you have target latency
比如，如果你有目标延迟时间
of 20 milliseconds and minimum granularity
20毫秒的延迟和最小粒度
of one millisecond,
一毫秒的时间，
then in this case, you can,
那么在这种情况下，你可以，
minimum granularity is going to prevail and is going,
最小粒度将会占主导地位并且正在发展。
you know, you cannot reduce the time slice
你知道，你不能减少时间片。
to less than one milliseconds.
小于一毫秒。
And, you know, the target latency, you cannot do it
而且，你知道的，目标延迟是无法实现的。
if you just do round robin, right?
如果你只是做轮询，对吗？
Because if you do round robin,
因为如果你使用循环赛制，
it's going to take 100 milliseconds
需要100毫秒。
to a process to get it's turn.
等待一个过程获得它的轮次。
So you need to wait for 99 milliseconds to get your turn.
所以你需要等待99毫秒才能轮到你。
So of course, we are going to violate
当然，我们会违反。
the target latency here.
这里的目标延迟是什么？
Okay?
好的？
Okay, it's a question here.
好的，这是一个问题。
Oh, what is granularity?
哦，granularity是什么意思？
Oh,
哦，
yeah.
是的。
Okay, so these are very good questions.
好的，这些是非常好的问题。
So what is granularity?
什么是粒度？
Granularity is how granular you are going to,
细粒度是指你要达到的粒度大小。
what is the granularity at which you are going
你打算以什么粒度进行？
to provide the service?
提供这项服务？
I mean, it's, this is what we mean.
我的意思是，这就是我们的意思。
It's like, what we mean is about
这个，我们的意思是关于什么的
what is the minimum length of the time slice in this case?
在这种情况下，时间片的最小长度是多少？
This is what I mean by granularity.
这就是我所说的"粒度"的意思。
What is the time slice size?
时间片大小是多少？
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese text into English and any non-Chinese text into Chinese. Please provide me with the content you need to be translated.
Why would we have both?
为什么我们需要两者都有？
It seems like minimum length is the only real
似乎最小长度是唯一真实的。
powerful constraint.
强大的限制。
Yes, you are correct.
是的，你是正确的。
And this is, in this example, we illustrated that.
而在这个例子中，我们展示了这一点。
That minimum granularity is a stronger constraint
最小粒度是一个更强的约束条件。
if you want, because if you go too low,
如果你愿意的话，因为如果你降得太低，
then the system doesn't, may not do any work, right?
那么系统就不会做任何工作，对吗？
It's, again, spend all the time doing context switching.
又要花费所有的时间来进行上下文切换。
But target latency, it's also a constraint if you want,
但是目标延迟也是一个限制，如果你愿意的话。
you know, if you want to support interactive workloads.
你知道的，如果你想要支持交互式工作负载。
Right?
对吗？
How we are going to, you know, it's,
我们要怎么做，你知道的，这个，
there is, there has to be, there are limits
有限制，必须有限制，存在限制。
in terms of how responsive your editor
就您的编辑器的响应性而言
or your computer should be,
或者你的电脑应该是的。
different applications should be,
不同的应用程序应该是，
to provide you a good experience.
为了给您提供良好的体验。
Okay?
好的。
So you should strive to provide that kind of level
所以你应该努力提供那种水平。
of interactivity and the level of interactivity,
互动性的程度和水平
it's obviously related with this target latency.
这显然与目标延迟有关。
Right?
对吗？
Because if you, if you are going, if the target latency,
因为如果你，如果你要去，如果目标延迟，
you know, like if you cannot get your turn,
你知道的，就像如果你不能轮到你。
say in 500 milliseconds, this means that your application,
在500毫秒内，这意味着您的应用程序，
you know, you may wait, you may have to wait
你知道，你可能需要等待，你可能不得不等待。
for half a second for your application to respond,
等待半秒钟以使您的应用程序响应，
your text application, editor, whatever.
你的文本应用程序，编辑器，或者其他什么。
So in summary, yes, the minimum granularity,
所以总结一下，是的，最小粒度，
it's a stronger constraint,
这是一个更严格的限制。
but target latency captures the demands
但目标延迟捕捉了需求。
of the interactive applications.
交互式应用程序。
So it's also important.
所以这也很重要。
The other question here is about priority,
这里的另一个问题是关于优先级的。
like this kind of a little bit prioritization.
喜欢这种稍微有点优先级排序。
What if we want to give more CPU to some,
如果我们想要给某些人更多的CPU资源，该怎么办？
to some threads or less to another,
对于一些帖子，或者对于另一些帖子来说，可能会更少。
so allowed for different rate of execution,
因此允许不同的执行速率，
is very similar.
非常相似。
It's like, it's a weight, it's like you give,
这就像是一个负担，就像是你付出了。
you give a weight in some sense, you see that is W.
你在某种意义上给了一个权重，你看到的是W。
So basically you have the equal share is basically the,
所以基本上你有平等的份额基本上是这样的，
the equal share here, it's about how much of the CPU
这里的"equal share"是指CPU的使用量。
you are going to give and its target latency over there,
你将提供它的目标延迟。
right, like we discussed earlier on.
没错，就像我们之前讨论过的那样。
And here is a way to sharing, you are going to basically,
而这是一种分享的方式，你基本上要做的是，
you are going to give within one of these target shares,
你将在这些目标股份中选择一个。
you are going to run one thread more times, multiple times.
你将要多次运行一个线程。
Okay, so this is very, very similar,
好的，所以这非常非常相似，
but it's using different notation,
但它使用了不同的符号表示法，
but the outcome is basically identical.
但结果基本上是相同的。
It's another implementation to having different number
这是另一种实现不同数字的方法。
of tickets, to giving different number of tickets
票的数量，给予不同数量的票
to different threads or processes, right?
对，是指不同的线程或进程，对吗？
So that's basically what it is, right?
那基本上就是这样，对吗？
So this is basic equal share, it's one over N.
所以这是基本的平均分配，即每个人分到的份额是总数的倒数。
And if you want weighted share, you do W,
如果你想要加权份额，你需要使用W。
you give up higher weight to one process.
你将更高的权重放在一个过程上。
And this, so then you get the fraction
这样，你就得到了分数。
you are going to get from the CPU.
你将从CPU获取。
It's your weight divided by the sum of the weights
这是你的体重除以所有体重之和。
of all the other threads or processes.
所有其他的线程或进程中。
And they use a value nice,
他们使用了一个很好的价值观。
value to reflect shares rather than priority.
将价值反映为股份而不是优先权。
And this is over using an API, an existing API,
而且这是通过使用一个API来完成的，一个已经存在的API。
and this is how you use it.
这是你如何使用它。
You have the nice is becoming the exponent.
你有很好的潜力。
This is how you are basically think about that.
这就是你基本上对此的想法。
When you are going to use nice, what will happen?
当你要使用"nice"时，会发生什么？
You are going to change the weight
你要改变重量。
as provided by this formula, right?
是的，按照这个公式提供的。
So your weight by default is 1024 over 125, it's 1024.
所以你的默认体重是1024除以125，等于1024。
If you are going to increase your nice,
如果你打算提升你的友善程度，
so you have to basically being nice,
所以你基本上要友善一点，
it means that you get less access to the CPU.
这意味着你对CPU的访问权限减少了。
So you let others use a CPU for longer, right?
所以你让别人使用CPU的时间更长，对吗？
That means to be nice.
这意味着要友善。
And this is reflected in getting a lower weight.
这反映在获得更低的重量上
And the way you, again, the particular weight
而且你，再一次，特定的重量方式
you are going to get by using nice
你会通过友善获得成功。
is given by this formula 1024 over 1.25 at power nice.
这个公式给出的结果是1024除以1.25的乘方9。
And it's here just to give you a sense,
而它只是在这里给你一个感觉，
if it's nice, it's incremented of in terms of incremented.
如果它很好，它会按增量递增。
If you remember, it's that you can increment
如果你记得的话，就是可以递增的。
units of five, 1.25 power five is three, right?
五的幂次是1.25的五次方是三，对吗？
So if you increase your nice by five,
那么如果你将你的好感度增加五分，
this means that your weight will decrease by three.
这意味着你的体重会减少三个单位。
Okay, yeah, there is a concept of virtual time.
好的，是的，有一个虚拟时间的概念。
We are not going to discuss it here,
我们不打算在这里讨论它。
but if you have questions,
但是如果你有问题，
I'll be more than happy to talk about this virtual time.
我非常乐意讨论这个虚拟时间。
I did a lot of research during my PhD
我在博士期间进行了很多研究。
many years back on this one.
很多年前的这个问题。
So really, really again, scheduling is a complex problem.
所以，真的，真的再次强调，排班是一个复杂的问题。
There are many hundreds of scheduling algorithms,
有很多数百种调度算法，
hundreds, thousands of research papers
数百篇、数千篇研究论文
that are probably only about,
大概只有，
you know, just talking about fair queuing
你知道，只是在谈论公平排队。
or proportional sharing is the same name
或者比例分享是同一个名称。
for the kind of the same scheduler,
对于相同类型的调度程序，
but in different domains like CPU or networking.
但在不同的领域，比如CPU或网络。
There are probably hundreds or thousands of papers
可能有数百或数千篇论文。
only for this particular discipline, okay?
只针对这个特定的学科，好吗？
So it's huge.
这么大。
And why is that?
为什么这样呢？
Is because, you know, the scheduler is hard
因为，你知道的，调度器很难。
because you want to do it extremely fast.
因为你想要做得非常快。
And then there are different competing priorities,
然后有不同的竞争优先事项，
competing demands from the applications, right?
是的，来自各个应用程序的竞争需求。
You want to be fair, you want to be interactive,
你想要公平，你想要互动，
you want to have high throughput and so forth.
你想要高吞吐量等等。
And therefore, that's why for different demands
因此，这就是为什么有不同的需求。
from the applications,
从应用程序中，
you can come up with different schedulers,
你可以提出不同的调度器，
which are best fit to satisfy those demands.
哪些是最适合满足这些需求的选择。
So for instance, if you want CPU throughput,
那么例如，如果你想要CPU的吞吐量，
it's first come first serve
先到先得
because what you want to minimize,
因为你想要最小化的东西，
you want to minimize the overhead for the scheduler.
你想要减少调度器的开销。
First come first serve, picking a new job,
先到先得，选择一份新工作，
it's super easy, it's all fun, right?
这很简单，都是有趣的，对吧？
It's ahead of the queue.
它在队列的前面。
And then there is no context switching.
然后就没有上下文切换了。
And you are going to continue to run that job to completion.
你将继续运行该任务直至完成。
Okay?
好的？
So minimizing the operation to select,
因此，将选择操作最小化，
you know, the overhead to select the next job,
你知道，选择下一个工作的开销，
minimizes the overhead, the number of context switches.
减少开销，减少上下文切换的次数。
Average response time is shortest time first, right?
平均响应时间是最短时间优先，对吗？
This is provable optimal
这是可以证明的最优解。
to minimize average response time.
为了最小化平均响应时间。
And so forth, you know, fairness here,
等等，你知道的，这里要公平，
you have Linux CFS, you can lay lottery scheduling.
你有Linux CFS，你可以使用抽签调度。
This is for CPU time.
这是用于CPU时间的。
Also fairness, and fairness,
公平性，还有公平性，
if you want to be very predictable
如果你想要变得非常可预测的话
or however long to wait until to get the CPU,
或者等待多长时间才能获得CPU，
just do the round robin.
请执行轮流制。
This is related to target latency,
这与目标延迟有关。
meeting the early deadline first.
首先满足提前截止日期。
If you want to have some very few important tasks,
如果你想要有一些非常少但重要的任务，
which they cannot be delayed, you can use priority.
如果有些事情不能延迟，你可以使用优先权。
And for IO support is SRDP approximation.
而对于IO支持，是SRDP近似。
Again, we discuss about that, I think two lectures ago,
再次，我们讨论那个问题，我记得是在两节课之前。
where we have these examples of two tasks,
我们有这两个任务的例子在哪里？
which each of them takes one week,
每个人都需要一周的时间。
and then you have this other task, which is IO bounded,
然后你还有另一个任务，这个任务是I/O受限的。
takes, runs for one millisecond
需要，运行一毫秒
and waits for nine milliseconds, if I remember correctly.
并且等待九毫秒，如果我没记错的话。
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
Now how to evaluate this scheduling algorithms, right?
现在要评估这些调度算法，对吗？
You have all of those different properties,
你拥有所有这些不同的特性，
how, and you are going to design them,
你打算如何设计它们？
how you are going to evaluate it.
你打算如何评估它。
There are several ways.
有几种方法。
First of all, deterministic.
首先，确定性的。
You basically, you get a workload
你基本上会得到一份工作量。
and given this workload,
鉴于这个工作量，
you compute the performance of the algorithms
你计算算法的性能。
in the face of that workload.
面对那么多的工作量。
Performance meaning, response times, throughput,
性能意义，响应时间，吞吐量。
latency, whatever metrics you care about
延迟，无论你关心的指标是什么。
for your application, right?
是为了你的申请，对吗？
And a deterministic preterm workload,
以及一个确定性的早产工作负载，
you say, okay, you are going to have,
你说，好的，你要去做什么？
each processes continue,
每个进程都在继续进行。
one process, you have one process arriving
一个进程，你有一个进程到达。
every one seconds,
每一秒钟，
and each process is going to have,
每个过程都会有，
10 seconds or so of compute, right?
大约需要10秒钟的计算时间，对吗？
Or things like that, okay?
还有类似的事情，好吗？
Queuing models.
排队模型。
This is a mathematical approach for stochastic workloads.
这是一种针对随机工作负载的数学方法。
So in this particular case,
因此在这个特定情况下，
basically you are saying that
基本上你是在说
the load is non-deterministic, right?
负载是非确定性的，对吗？
You give the load in statistical terms,
你以统计术语给出了负载。
is all you say on the average,
你说的都是平均值吗？
you have one process arriving every seconds.
你每秒钟有一个进程到达。
And this process on the average has,
而这个过程平均来说，
it takes, running time is 10 seconds.
需要，运行时间为10秒。
And those numbers are drawn from a particular distribution.
这些数字是从特定的分布中抽取的。
Like for instance, the length of that process
比如说，那个过程的长度。
is exponentially distributed, right?
是指数分布，对吗？
The average, the mean is 10 seconds.
平均值为10秒。
And the arrival time is like say,
而到达时间就像是说，
Poisson distributed.
泊松分布。
Poisson means that the inter arrival between processes
泊松意味着进程之间的到达间隔
is drawn from an exponential distribution.
服从指数分布。
This is just an example.
这只是一个例子。
And for that, you are going to get statistic,
而为此，你将获得统计数据。
you are going to be able to compute statistically,
你将能够进行统计计算。
what are the performance of the scheduler,
调度器的性能如何？
like for instance, again, mean response time,
例如，再举一个例子，平均响应时间，
or anything like that.
或者类似的东西。
And the other one, you just implement it,
而另一个，你只需要实施它。
you just text, Python,
你刚刚发了一条短信，内容是Python。
you implement a simple simulator and run it,
您实现了一个简单的模拟器并运行它。
and see what results you get.
然后看看你得到什么结果。
This is general flexible,
这是一般灵活的。
as long as you don't have bugs in your simulator.
只要你的模拟器没有bug。
So,
所以，
a final word on scheduling.
关于日程安排的最后一句话。
The scheduling matters
日程安排事项
when there are not enough resources.
当资源不足时。
And many of the things we learn in this class,
而我们在这门课上学到的许多东西，
many of the algorithms and many of the problem we solve,
我们解决的许多算法和问题
these problems occur
这些问题发生了。
because there are not enough resources.
因为资源不足。
We'll see virtual memory.
我们将看到虚拟内存。
Why do we have virtual memory that I'm that?
为什么我们需要虚拟内存？它是用来做什么的？
Oh, because there is not enough physical memory.
哦，因为物理内存不足。
It's one of the reasons.
这是其中一个原因。
No, right?
不是吗？
Scheduling.
排程。
Why do we need to have a scheduling,
为什么我们需要有一个日程安排？
a sophisticated scheduling?
一个复杂的日程安排？
Because there are not enough CPUs.
因为CPU数量不足。
If you have one CPU per thread,
如果每个线程都有一个CPU，
there is no scheduling, right?
没有安排计划，对吗？
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese text into English and any non-Chinese text into Chinese. Please provide me with the content you would like me to translate.
Why should you simply buy a faster computer or highways?
为什么你应该简单地购买一台更快的电脑或高速公路呢？
Well, look, you can buy it if you can afford it.
好吧，看吧，如果你买得起的话就买吧。
But remember, the more slow is ending.
但请记住，结束得越慢。
So now if you buy a new computer, you could buy your Mac or your PC, it's not a lot of
所以现在如果你买一台新电脑，你可以买Mac或PC，选择并不多。
more powerful than the one you have from three years back.
比你三年前的那个更强大。
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
And of course, you need to be careful about not...
当然，你需要小心不要...
You don't want to spend too much money.
你不想花太多钱。
The other thing what you need to understand, and this is a curve on this right hand side,
你需要理解的另一件事是，这是右侧的一个曲线。
maybe you should do a lecture on it because it's extremely important.
也许你应该做一个关于这个话题的讲座，因为它非常重要。
It's an extremely important curve.
这是一个非常重要的曲线。
And this is what I say this curve.
这是我对这条曲线的看法。
Say your system has a certain capacity.
你的系统有一定的容量。
When you are approaching the capacity of the system, the response time is growing super
当系统接近容量时，响应时间会变得非常长。
linearly.
线性地。
This almost goes to infinity if you go to 100%.
这几乎无限接近于百分之百，如果你达到100%。
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
And again, we don't have time here to say why, but intuitively think about the highway
再说一遍，我们没有时间在这里解释为什么，但直观地想一想高速公路。
and the rush hour.
和高峰时间。
So it's like the difference where you start to be to approach the capacity of the highway.
所以这就像是你开始接近高速公路容量的差异。
And if you just inject a few cars, a few more cars, then the delay is going to shut up.
如果你只是增加几辆车，再增加几辆车，那么延误就会减少。
For instance, if there are on the highway, now there are 100 cars per hour and the capacity
例如，如果在高速公路上，现在每小时有100辆车，而道路的容量是200辆车。
of the system is 120.
系统的总和是120。
And now you have a speed and the latency is 50 miles per hour.
现在你有了速度，延迟是每小时50英里。
Now if you add 10 more cars, so it's still a less than capacity.
现在如果再增加10辆车，那么仍然不会达到容量。
Instead of going 50 miles per hour, you are going to go suddenly 20 miles per hour.
不再以每小时50英里的速度前进，而是突然以每小时20英里的速度前进。
And again, think about your experience.
再次思考一下你的经验。
Just a few more cars, everything can bring everything to a crawl.
只要再多几辆车，就会导致一切都陷入瘫痪。
So again, let me see where I can have a lecture on that.
所以，让我再看看我可以在哪里听到关于那个的讲座。
So now, let me see.
那么现在，让我看看。
What if all the cars are managed by computer and all of them move simultaneously?
如果所有的汽车都由计算机管理，并且它们同时移动，会怎样呢？
Yeah, in that case, you can achieve the capacity.
是的，在那种情况下，你可以达到这个能力。
But the point is that that's not the case.
但问题是，事实并非如此。
And the car leaves gap between them and these gaps, you cannot recover them.
车辆之间留下了间隙，这些间隙是无法弥补的。
So these gaps take from the capacity of the system.
所以这些间隙会占用系统的容量。
That's kind of the intuition.
这有点直觉。
So announcements.
所以，公告。
I know that everyone waits for that.
我知道每个人都在等待那个。
Mittermon, we are planning to release the grades by next Monday.
Mittermon，我们计划在下周一发布成绩。
So we are grading your Mittermon.
我们正在给你的Mittermon评分。
Project due is due this Wednesday.
项目截止日期是本周三。
Code, final report, peer evaluation, everything.
代码，最终报告，同行评估，全部都有。
If any of them is late, you are going to incur sleep days.
如果其中任何一个人迟到，你将会承担睡眠日的损失。
Okay, remember that.
好的，记住了。
Group evaluation coming for Project ON, right?
是的，项目ON要进行小组评估，对吗？
Every person, I believe you get 20 points per partner, which, you know, so everyone,
每个人，我相信你们每个人都会得到20分，这样每个人都会得到。
every person get 20 points.
每个人得到20分
And you are going to hand out these points to other members in your group, not to yourself.
你将把这些积分分发给你们小组的其他成员，而不是给自己。
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese text into English and any non-Chinese text into Chinese. Please provide me with the content you would like to be translated.
So this is a way to measure what is the contribution of other members in your team.
这是一种衡量团队其他成员贡献的方法。
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
Office hours.
办公时间。
You know, there are a lot of students, and we all want to, again, to answer all your
你知道，有很多学生，我们都想要再次回答你的问题。
questions.
问题。
But like you say, like you see in this lecture, you know, when the resources are scared, we
但就像你所说的，就像你在这个讲座中所看到的那样，当资源稀缺时，我们
need to put some conditions, some policies in place, right, to try to provide some level
需要制定一些条件和政策，对吧，以试图提供一定程度的
of fairness to you guys.
为了对你们公平起见。
And so, TAs are spent, in general, are bound to spend 15 minutes per student.
因此，助教通常需要花费15分钟来处理一个学生的问题。
It's again to give, to not starve other students from their attention.
这句话的意思是“再次给予，不让其他学生因为注意力不集中而挨饿。”
And you need to have a detailed ticket filled out and the GDP pulled up, right?
是的，您需要填写一张详细的票据并提供GDP的数据，对吗？
So to be absolutely ready.
所以要绝对准备好。
So the context switching is minimal, right, between students.
所以学生之间的上下文切换是最小的，对吗？
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
And from these 15 minutes, you get the full value for these 15 minutes.
从这15分钟中，你会得到这15分钟的全部价值。
You don't have to wait for five minutes to set up your GDP and provide the ticket detail
你不需要等五分钟来设置你的GDP并提供票务详情。
explaining to the TA and thing like that.
向助教解释之类的事情。
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese text into English and any non-Chinese text into Chinese. Please provide me with the content you would like to be translated.
Great.
太好了。
So now we are going to switch gears and we are going to talk about deadlocks.
所以现在我们要转换话题，我们要谈论死锁。
And deadlock is a particular type of starvation.
死锁是一种特殊类型的饥饿现象。
Yes.
是的。
Thank you for, of course, this is, my date is wrong.
谢谢你，当然，这是我的错。
The Wednesday, it was Wednesday.
星期三，那天是星期三。
Thanks.
谢谢。
So deadlock is a deadly type of starvation.
死锁是一种致命的饥饿类型。
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese text into English and any non-Chinese text into Chinese. Please provide me with the content you need to be translated.
Starvation, the stress may wait indefinitely, right?
饥饿，压力可能会无限期地等待，对吗？
Allow priorities, try waiting for resources, because there are many other high priority
请允许优先级，尝试等待资源，因为还有许多其他高优先级的任务。
threats.
威胁。
The deadlock, it's a circular waiting for resources.
死锁是指循环等待资源的情况。
And this is a very simple example.
这是一个非常简单的例子。
Say you have two threats and both threats in order to make progress, require to get
说你面临两个威胁，而为了取得进展，这两个威胁都需要得到...
access to two resources, resource one and resource two.
可以访问两个资源，资源一和资源二。
And now one threat gets access to resource one and the other said, get access to resource
现在一个威胁获得了资源一的访问权限，另一个威胁则获得了访问资源的权限。
two.
两个。
And both of them, they hold these resources.
而且他们两个都掌握着这些资源。
So none of them can get the other resource.
所以他们都无法获得对方的资源。
So they are deadlocked.
所以他们陷入了僵局。
They cannot make progress.
他们无法取得进展。
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese into English and any non-Chinese into Chinese. Please provide me with the text you would like to be translated.
This is what it is.
这就是它的样子。
So deadlock implies starvation.
所以死锁意味着饥饿。
Because starvation, because you are guaranteed that in a deadlock, now one will make progress.
因为饥饿，因为你保证在僵局中，现在没有人会取得进展。
Starvation doesn't imply deadlock because starvation can end.
饥饿并不意味着死锁，因为饥饿是可以结束的。
Eventually, if the high priority task finish, the low priority tasks can be executed.
最终，如果高优先级任务完成，低优先级任务可以被执行。
Deadlock cannot finish without some external intervention.
死锁无法在没有外部干预的情况下结束。
Here is example.
这是一个例子。
It's a real example.
这是一个真实的例子。
It's a one line bridge.
这是一座单行桥。
And as you probably know it, if you went to Yosemite on California on 140.
而且你可能知道，如果你去加利福尼亚的优胜美地，需要走140号公路。
And so the point here is, again, there are two directions.
所以这里的重点是，再次强调有两个方向。
Now typically you have a traffic light for these ones.
现在通常情况下，这些地方都会有一个交通信号灯。
But assume that you don't have a traffic light.
但是假设你没有交通信号灯。
So if you don't have a traffic light, what happens?
如果你没有交通信号灯，会发生什么情况？
What can happen intuitively?
直觉上会发生什么？
What is the problem?
什么问题？(What is the problem?)
The problem is that two cars come from both ends.
问题是两辆车从两端驶来。
And because there is no line, they are stuck.
而且因为没有排队
They are deadlocked.
他们陷入了僵局。
And the way you can model this is basically thinking that you have two halves to the entrance,
而你可以建模的方式基本上是将入口分为两半，
two halves of the bridge.
桥的两半。
And each car acquire one half.
每辆车都获得一半。
But in order to cross the bridge, you need two both halves.
但是为了过桥，你需要两个完整的半部分。
So it's exactly like the previous example.
所以它和之前的例子完全一样。
Each car has one half.
每辆车都有一半。
Each car require both halves.
每辆车都需要两个半部分。
They are stuck.
他们被困住了。
So in order, how you solve this, the only way to solve this deadlock is for one car
所以按顺序，你解决这个问题的唯一方法是让一辆车解决这个僵局。
to back up.
备份。
And this is equivalent with the other car who didn't back up to preempt the resource
这与另一辆没有倒车以预防资源的车辆相等。
which is hauled by the car who backed up.
由倒车的汽车拖拉的是什么？
Because now the car which didn't back up is going to acquire the second half of the bridge.
因为现在那辆没有倒车的车要通过桥的后半段了。
Now it has the first half, second half, and then it's going to cross the bridge.
现在它有上半场，下半场，然后它要过桥了。
Now the equivalent of starvation here is basically saying you have a lot of cars from one side
现在，"饥饿"在这里的等效说法基本上是指一边有很多车辆。
east and you have cars after car after car and the car which comes from the other direction
东边有一辆又一辆的车，还有一辆从另一个方向来的车。
will not get an opportunity even to get on the bridge.
连上桥的机会都没有。
Just starvation.
只是饥饿。
Again, starvation eventually can end when there are no longer cars coming in this case
再次，当没有车辆进来的时候，饥饿最终会结束。
from the west or from the east.
从西方还是从东方来。
Now let's look about what does it seem from the point of view of the program.
现在让我们从程序的角度来看看它看起来是什么样子。
You have two threads here and let's go to, you know, it's like locks, right?
你这里有两个线程，我们来说说，就像锁一样，对吧？
These resources are like locks.
这些资源就像锁一样。
Locks are resources.
锁是资源。
And this figure and the examples we consider so far can be expressed the following way.
这个数字和我们目前考虑的例子可以用以下方式表示。
Thread A, you have two locks, X and Y.
线程A，你有两个锁，X和Y。
Acquires lock X and Y and then releases Y and X.
获取锁X和Y，然后释放Y和X。
And B, acquires the locks in the different order and releases them in the different order.
并且B以不同的顺序获取锁，并以不同的顺序释放锁。
So in this case, you can get that lock, right?
那么在这种情况下，你可以得到那个锁，对吗？
When does this happen?
这是什么时候发生的？
Well, when this kind of order, you know, the CPU interleaves execution of instruction from
好的，当这种指令执行时，你知道，CPU会交错执行指令。
different threads.
不同的线程。
So for instance, when this happens on thread A acquire X, then thread B acquire Y, now
所以例如，当这在线程A上发生时获取X，然后线程B获取Y，现在
thread A is stalled because thread B owns Y and thread B cannot progress further either
线程A被阻塞了，因为线程B拥有Y，而且线程B也无法继续进行。
because it wants to acquire X, which is owned by A. So this is that lock, right?
因为它想要收购A所拥有的X。所以这就是那个锁，对吗？
Start to debug because this happens, now doesn't happen all the time.
开始调试，因为出现了这个问题，但现在并不是每次都会发生。
And again, you want to avoid it.
再次，你想要避免它。
Because it's again, like for instance, if this happens, you don't have that lock, right?
因为这又是一个例子，比如说，如果发生这种情况，你就没有那个锁，对吧？
So this is non-terministic.
所以这是非确定性的。
It will be a non-terministic bug, right?
这将是一个非确定性的错误，对吗？
And you always need to be afraid of non-terministic bugs because you cannot reproduce them.
而且你总是需要担心非确定性错误，因为你无法复现它们。
If you can reproduce a bug, it's relatively easy to fix it.
如果你能够复现一个bug，修复它相对来说是比较容易的。
If you cannot reproduce it, how you are going to fix it?
如果你无法复现它，你将如何修复它？
Here is another classic example.
这是另一个经典的例子。
Here are four trains and in this configuration, none of them can make progress.
这里有四列火车，按照这个配置，它们都无法前进。
You have a deadlock.
你遇到了死锁。
So you have here a deadlock just basically to illustrate the point.
所以你这里有一个死锁，基本上只是为了说明这一点。
So far, the examples we had, you have two entities which are in deadlock, two cars or
到目前为止，我们所举的例子中，你有两个处于僵局的实体，两辆车或者...
two threads.
两个线程。
But obviously, deadlock can happen between multiple, more than two entities.
但显然，死锁可能发生在多个、超过两个实体之间。
And here is an example for four.
这里是一个关于四的例子。
So here each train wants to turn to right.
所以这里每一辆火车都想要向右转。
This is real.
这是真的。
This is a real problem which are in different systems, encountering different systems.
这是一个真正的问题，涉及到不同的系统，遇到不同的系统。
Yeah.
是的。
Yes, it's exactly San Francisco traffic.
是的，这正是旧金山的交通情况。
Yeah, that's a good one.
是的，那个不错。
So how you fix it?
那么你是如何修复它的呢？
So one way to fix it, it's actually for some ordering.
所以解决的一种方法，实际上是进行一些排序。
You'll see this as a recurrent theme.
你会看到这是一个反复出现的主题。
One way to fix deadlock is to have an order.
解决死锁的一种方法是确定一个顺序。
So for instance, in this case, always go east, west first and north, south, then back first.
所以例如，在这种情况下，始终先向东，然后向西，再向北，最后向南，然后再返回。
Don't go north, south and east, west.
不要往北、南、东、西走。
Only east, west and north, south.
只有东、西、南、北。
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
And as you'll see, like for our previous example, okay, so this is a lot.
而且你会看到，就像我们之前的例子一样，好的，所以这是很多的。
So as you see in our previous examples, when you have this kind of deadlock, and we'll
因此，正如你在我们之前的例子中所看到的那样，当你遇到这种死锁情况时，我们将...
say it a few more times, but it's good to remember, that one way you can avoid the deadlock
再说几遍，但要记住，你可以避免僵局的一种方法是
in the previous case is to enforce that both threads are going to acquire the locks in
在前一个案例中，目的是确保两个线程都会获取锁。
the same order.
相同的顺序。
So again, if I go back here, if you enforce that both A and B acquire threads in the same
所以，如果我再回到这里，如果你强制要求A和B同时获取线程，那么
order, first X and then Y, you are going to solve this problem.
请先解决X问题，然后再解决Y问题。
And again, we have the deadlock here because we do not have enough resources.
我们又陷入了僵局，因为我们没有足够的资源。
If we have enough resources, it's not a problem.
如果我们有足够的资源，这不是个问题。
You wait for a resource that multiple threads compete to.
你等待一个被多个线程竞争的资源。
There are also threads that are blocking waiting for other threads like pipe or sockets or
还有一些线程正在等待其他线程，比如管道或套接字。
wait like for instance, I am blocked to wait for a get to get a message.
等一下，比如说，我被阻止等待一个获取消息的请求。
What I am waiting for, if I am remember about bounded queues, I am waiting for queue to
如果我记得正确的话，我正在等待有界队列。我正在等待队列。
become to get a free slot in order if I am a producer, I can wait if the queue is full,
如果我是制片人，我可以等待，即使队列已满，也能获得一个免费的时间段。
I am waiting until the queue is drained so I can put more and more items in the queue.
我正在等待队列被清空，这样我就可以不断地向队列中添加更多的项目。
So it's again, deadlock with space is an example like here.
所以又是一次，僵局与空间是一个例子，就像这里一样。
If you don't have enough resources, you have two threads, each threads want to allocate
如果你没有足够的资源，你有两个线程，每个线程都想分配资源。
two megabytes, but they want to allocate that in two different calls.
两兆字节，但他们想要分两次分配。
And now assume that you have two megabytes of space.
现在假设你有两兆字节的空间。
So each thread allocates two megabytes, three two megabytes, but it's doing that one megabyte
所以每个线程分配两兆字节，三个两兆字节，但它只使用了一兆字节。
at a time.
一次。
So you can get here a deadlock situation because if one thread gets one megabyte and one thread
所以你可能会遇到死锁的情况，因为如果一个线程获取了一个兆字节，而另一个线程获取了一个
gets another one megabyte, they are deadlocked because none of the thread can get an extra
得到另外一个兆字节，它们陷入了僵局，因为没有一个线程能够获得额外的。
megabyte in order to finish.
兆字节以完成。
Okay, so here is another very famous problem to illustrate the deadlock.
好的，这里有另一个非常著名的问题来说明死锁。
I think it was called philosopher problem.
我认为它被称为哲学家问题。
This is a little bit of a joke with the lawyers.
这是一个关于律师的小笑话。
But think about this, you have five people and there are only five chopsticks.
但是想想看，你有五个人，只有五根筷子。
Now in order to eat, you need two chopsticks.
现在为了吃饭，你需要两根筷子。
So if everyone grabs one chopstick, it's deadlock because no one can eat.
所以如果每个人都拿一根筷子，就会陷入僵局，因为没有人能吃饭。
So how do you do that?
那么你是如何做到的呢？
Well, in order to break this deadlock, you need to give someone two chopsticks.
好的，为了打破这个僵局，你需要给某人两根筷子。
So if everyone has one chopstick, we need to get someone to give up her chopstick to
another person so that everyone has a pair of chopsticks.
her neighbor.
她的邻居。
So now the neighbor has two chopsticks.
所以现在邻居有两根筷子。
She can eat, she can finish, and now she can give the chopsticks to her neighbors.
她可以吃，她可以吃完，现在她可以把筷子给她的邻居。
And now her neighbors can finish.
现在她的邻居们可以完成了。
So this was solving the deadlock after it occurred.
这样就解决了死锁发生后的问题。
But of course, ideally, you even want to prevent that lock.
当然，理想情况下，你甚至希望避免那种锁定的情况发生。
So you have to have an algorithm if you want to prevent the deadlock, you don't get in
所以如果你想要防止死锁，你必须要有一个算法，你就不会陷入其中。
the deadlock situation in the first case.
第一个案例中的僵局局势。
We'll talk about those, but keep that in mind.
我们会谈论那些事情，但请记住这一点。
Now if you remember, when you have these kind of situations, you have some concurrency,
现在如果你记得的话，当你遇到这种情况时，你会有一些并发。
this is also an example of concurrent access to the resources.
这也是对资源的并发访问的一个例子。
We saw something similar with this when we talk about critical section.
我们在谈论临界区时，发现了类似的情况。
We really want to have some to formalize the problem.
我们真的希望有人能够将问题形式化。
And if we formalize a problem and say, what are the conditions a solution should meet,
如果我们将一个问题形式化，并且问，解决方案应该满足什么条件，
then we should focus on, we can only focus when developing a solution to meeting these
然后我们应该专注于，只有在开发解决方案以满足这些需求时，我们才能集中精力。
conditions.
条件。
So what are the requirements?
那么，有哪些要求呢？
First of all, let's think about when does a deadlock occurs.
首先，让我们思考一下死锁是在什么时候发生的。
Because if we know the requirements on the deadlock occurs, then if we basically break
因为如果我们知道死锁发生的要求，那么如果我们基本上打破了这些要求，死锁就不会发生。
one of these requirements, then we can break the deadlock.
如果满足这些要求之一，我们就可以打破僵局。
So there are four requirements for a deadlock docker.
所以一个死锁的docker有四个要求。
Mutual exclusion.
互斥。
Only once at a time can use a resource.
每次只能同时使用一个资源。
Hold and wait.
请稍等。
A threat holding at least one resource
一个威胁至少掌握一种资源
is waiting to acquire additional resources
正在等待获取额外资源
held by other threats.
受到其他威胁的困扰。
Because if you don't wait, you can proceed,
因为如果你不等待，你可以继续进行。
you can finish it.
你可以完成它。
You can release a resource
你可以释放一个资源。
and now there are no resources in the system.
现在系统中没有资源了。
So maybe other threats can finish
所以也许其他威胁可以结束
which you're waiting for the resources you are holding.
你正在等待你所持有的资源。
No preemption.
不可抢占。
If a threat holds a resource,
如果威胁掌握了一项资源，
that threat is not going to release a resource voluntarily.
那个威胁不会自愿释放资源
Okay?
好的。
Before it finishes with it.
在它完成之前。
And then it is circular wait.
然后就是循环等待。
There exists a set of threats
存在一系列的威胁。
such that T1 is waiting for a resource
这样T1就在等待一个资源。
that is held by T2,
这是由T2持有的。
T2 is waiting for a resource
T2正在等待一个资源。
that is held by T3 and so forth.
这是由T3等人持有的。
So this means the last,
这意味着最后一个，
the last actually requirement
最后的实际要求
give us a way to detect deadlocks.
给我们一种检测死锁的方法。
Okay?
好的。
So how is that?
那样怎么样？
So basically you want to detect that cycle.
所以基本上你想要检测出那个循环。
So let's use the same symbols.
那么让我们使用相同的符号。
You already use them, but.
你已经在使用它们了，但是。
The threats are circles.
威胁是圆圈。
The resources are rectangles
资源是矩形。
and you have multiple dots.
你有多个点。
So this resource,
这个资源，
each dot represent an instance of a particular resource.
每个点代表一个特定资源的实例。
So for instance, you have a CPU is four cores.
所以例如，你有一个四核的CPU。
You are going to have four dots,
你将会有四个点，
each representing one core.
每个代表一个核心。
Okay?
好的。
And the pattern of manipulating a resource is very simple.
而且操纵资源的模式非常简单。
You request the resource, you use the resource,
您请求资源，您使用资源，
you release the resource after you are done.
你在完成后释放资源。
And now we can have a resource allocation graph.
现在我们可以有一个资源分配图。
And there are two types of,
而且有两种类型的，
we have two types of vertices,
我们有两种类型的顶点。
threads and resources, resource types,
线程和资源，资源类型。
and two types of vertices or edges.
和两种类型的顶点或边。
Sorry, and two types of edges.
抱歉，还有两种类型的边缘。
These are directed edge.
这些是有向边。
If a thread, you have a edge from a thread TI
如果是线程，你有一个来自线程TI的边缘。
to a resource RJ,
给一个资源 RJ，
if thread TI request the resource J.
如果线程TI请求资源J。
And then you have assignment edge,
然后你有作业边缘。
which it's a direct edge from RJ
这是一个直接从RJ边缘开始的边缘。
to thread TI,
将TI线程化
when thread TI allocates
当线程TI分配时
or has allocated resource RJ.
或者已分配资源RJ。
Okay?
好的。
So basically here in this example,
所以基本上在这个例子中，
this edge from R1 to T2 basically says that T2 own R1.
这条从R1到T2的边基本上表示T2拥有R1。
The edge from T1 to R1 says that T1 request resource R1.
从T1到R1的边表示T1请求资源R1。
Okay?
好的。
So this is some examples.
这是一些例子。
Okay?
好的。
So you see here,
所以你看到这里，
let's see which are,
让我们看看有哪些。
it turns out and we are going to learn more about that,
原来如此，我们将会进一步了解这个。
but it turns out that this middle examples,
但事实证明，这些中间的例子，
it seems that that look.
看起来好像是那个样子。
Why?
为什么？
Because two reasons.
因为两个原因。
First of all, you have a cycle.
首先，你有一个循环。
You see here,
你看到这里，
T1 was for R1,
T1是为了R1而设的。
which is own R1 is owned by T2.
R1是由T2拥有的。
And T2 ways are for R...
而T2方式是为了R...
Oh, I'm sorry.
哦，对不起。
I am sorry.
对不起。
The cycle is this one.
这个周期是这样的。
R3, T2, R2, T3.
R3, T2, R2, T3. (Translated from Chinese)
R3, T2, R2, T3. (Translated from English)
So T2 owns R3,
所以T2拥有R3。
request R2,
请求R2。
which is owned by T3.
这是由T3拥有的。
And finally, T3 request for R3,
最后，T3向R3发出请求。
which is owned by T2.
这个是由T2拥有的。
So this is a deadlock because you have the cycle
这是一个死锁，因为你有一个循环。
and the other condition, if you remember here,
另外一个条件，如果你还记得的话，
another requirement is hold on wait.
另一个要求是等一下。
Threat holding at least one resource is waiting
威胁持有至少一项资源正在等待。
to acquire additional resource held by other threats.
获取其他威胁持有的额外资源。
So every threat here in this example,
所以在这个例子中，每一个威胁，
it's in this situation, right?
是在这种情况下，对吗？
It's waiting for a resource handled by another threat.
它正在等待由另一个线程处理的资源。
Here is an example,
这是一个例子，
which is, there is a cycle,
这是一个循环。
T1, R1, T3, R2.
T1, R1, T3, R2. (No translation needed)
But this is not deadlock
但这不是死锁。
because T2 and T4 own a resource,
因为T2和T4拥有一项资源，
but they don't do it for any other resource.
但是他们不会为任何其他资源这样做。
Okay?
好的。
And the reason this is not a deadlock,
而这不是一个死锁的原因是，
again, we'll learn more in the next,
再次，我们将在接下来的课程中学到更多。
in the remaining of this lecture and the next lecture,
在接下来的这节课和下一节课中，
is that T2 and T4 can proceed.
是的，T2和T4可以继续进行。
Can run to completion.
可以运行到完成。
And once they run to completion,
一旦它们运行完毕，
they free an instance of R1 and R2 respectively.
他们分别释放了R1和R2的实例。
I see, yeah.
我明白了，是的。
How does R3 have two assignment edges?
R3是如何有两条分配边的？
Assignment, good answer.
作业，好答案。
There are two instances.
有两个实例。
Yes, like I said, so you can look about this R3 and R4.
是的，就像我说的那样，你可以查看一下R3和R4。
As type of resources.
作为资源类型。
And the dots within these rectangles
这些矩形内的点
are the number of instances of that particular type.
这是那种特定类型的实例数量。
And typically one thread here
通常这里只有一个帖子。
will require one instance of a particular resource type.
需要一个特定资源类型的实例。
Okay.
Sure, I will translate your Chinese text into English and any non-Chinese text into Chinese. Please provide me with the content you would like to be translated.
So we do have also a deadlock detection algorithms.
所以我们也有死锁检测算法。
You want an algorithm.
你想要一个算法。
And the deadlock detection algorithms is very simple.
而且死锁检测算法非常简单。
Okay?
好的？
So you keep an array of free resources.
所以你保留了一个空闲资源的数组。
Then you have an array of requests,
然后你有一个请求的数组，
threads of the current, you know,
电流的线程，你知道的，
current request from thread X.
当前来自线程X的请求。
And you have also, so for each thread X,
而且你也有，所以对于每个线程X，
you have the current request of that thread
你有该线程的当前请求。
and the current resources are located by that thread.
并且当前的资源由该线程定位。
Okay?
好的。
So you initialize the available resources
所以你初始化可用资源
to the free resources, right?
对于免费的资源，对吗？
The free resources are the one which are available.
免费资源是那些可用的资源。
Then you look at all the nodes which are unfinished.
然后你看看所有未完成的节点。
You keep all the nodes, which are all threads.
你保留了所有的节点，这些节点都是线程。
This represents all threads, which are not finished.
这代表着所有未完成的线程。
And you take one by one,
然后你一个一个地拿。
and you look whether you have enough available resources
你看看你是否有足够的可用资源。
for that thread to finish.
等待那个线程完成。
In other words, if the requested resources
换句话说，如果请求的资源
by that thread can be satisfied
通过那个线程可以满足。
by the existing available resources.
根据现有的可用资源。
And if yes, you are going to run the thread,
如果是的话，你将会运行这个线程。
and then now all the resources, once the thread finishes
然后现在所有的资源，一旦线程完成
are going to be added to the availability.
将会添加到可用性中。
Set, because they are available now.
集合，因为它们现在可用。
Okay?
好的。
So you do that.
那么你就这样做吧。
And if there are no longer unfinished resources,
如果没有未完成的资源了，
when, if there are no longer items in,
当，如果没有物品在的话，
or threads in the finished list, you are done.
或者在已完成列表中的线程，你完成了。
There is not a deadlock.
没有僵局。
Otherwise, there is a deadlock.
否则，就会陷入僵局。
(silence)
对不起，我无法翻译空白的内容。请提供需要翻译的具体文本。
So not left in unfinished are deadlocked.
所以不要让未完成的事情陷入僵局。
Okay?
好的。
So let me, there is a question here,
所以让我来，这里有一个问题，
but T1 and T2, T3 is still in deadlock.
但是T1和T2，T3仍然处于僵局。
Oh, okay.
哦，好的。
So I can say, so, okay.
所以我可以说，那么，好的。
So let me say here.
那么让我在这里说一下。
So this is a question.
这是一个问题。
It's a great timing for that question.
这个时机很好，问得正好。
So,
所以，
so the question here, yes, you know, T2 and T4 finishes,
所以问题在这里，是的，你知道，T2和T4的完成情况。
but T1 and T3 are still in deadlock.
但是T1和T3仍然陷入僵局。
So here is a thing.
所以这里有一件事情。
If you run this algorithm, what will happen?
如果你运行这个算法，会发生什么？
You see, T2 actually will finish execution.
你知道，T2实际上会完成执行。
And once T2 finishes execution,
一旦T2执行完成，
it releases the instance of R1.
它释放了R1的实例。
Now there is one available R1 instance.
现在有一个可用的R1实例。
So T1 can acquire that instance.
所以T1可以获取那个实例。
And now T1 has both instance of R2 and R1.
现在T1同时拥有R2和R1的实例。
So it can run and complete.
所以它可以运行并完成。
Okay?
好的。
So that's a trick because the T2,
这是一个技巧，因为T2，
whenever you have a threat, which can complete,
无论何时你面临威胁，只要能够完成，
think that is going to release, you know,
我认为它即将发布，你知道的。
once it finishes, the number of free resources,
一旦完成，免费资源的数量将会
available resources is going to increase,
可用资源将会增加。
which will give an opportunity to other threat,
这将给其他威胁提供机会。
which are blocked until then, to acquire the newly,
这些在那之前被封锁的，以获取最新的，
the new release resources and to finish themself.
新发布的资源需要自己完成。
And then they're going to finish,
然后他们就要完成了。
even more resources are going to be available
将会有更多的资源可用。
for the, in the system for the other threats to finish.
为了，在系统中为了其他威胁的结束。
So how should we deal with a deadlock?
那么我们应该如何处理僵局呢？
There are four different approaches.
有四种不同的方法
Deadlock prevention,
死锁预防。
so you write your code in a way that is not,
所以你的代码是以一种不
deadlock cannot happen.
死锁不会发生。
It can't happen.
这是不可能的。
Deadlock recovery, you let the deadlock happen
死锁恢复，你让死锁发生了。
and then figure out how to recover from it.
然后找出如何从中恢复过来。
Remember it's those like, you know,
记住，就是那些，你知道的，
on the bridge, a car which can back up.
在桥上，有一辆可以倒车的汽车。
You can preempt the resource or things like that.
你可以预先占用资源或类似的东西。
Deadlock avoidance, with deadlock avoidance,
死锁避免，使用死锁避免方法，
you can dynamically delay resource requests
你可以动态延迟资源请求。
so deadlock doesn't happen.
所以死锁不会发生。
You can order and impose the order and the time
您可以下订单并确定订单和送货时间。
when different threats, they request resources.
当面临不同的威胁时，他们会请求资源。
Right, so now a very simple example from the beginning,
好的，现在给你一个非常简单的例子，从头开始，
if you remember, you just say, well, you know,
如果你记得的话，你只需要说，嗯，你知道的。
first you let duty one acquire the resources
首先，你让责任一获取资源。
and then duty two, and then there is no deadlock.
然后是第二个任务，然后就没有僵局了。
Well, the last one, you know,
最后一个，你知道的，
it's obviously not a solution.
这显然不是一个解决方案。
It's, you can deny the deadlock and see what happens.
可以的，你可以否认僵局，看看会发生什么。
Maybe you are lucky.
也许你很幸运。
What is the difference between deadlock avoidance
死锁避免和死锁检测的区别是什么？
and deadlock prevention?
死锁预防？
That's a very good question.
这是一个非常好的问题。
Deadlock avoidance is that you can write your code,
死锁避免是指你可以编写你的代码，
for instance, deadlock prevention, meaning that,
例如，死锁预防，意思是，
for instance, you make sure that you never had
例如，你确保你从来没有拥有过。
more threats than the resources.
比资源更多的威胁。
Right, you have plenty of resources.
没错，你有很多资源。
Then you prevent the deadlock.
那么你可以防止死锁。
Deadlock avoidance is that deadlock can happen,
死锁避免是指死锁可能发生，
but you can make sure and you write your,
但你可以确保并且你自己写。
you know, your code and you are trying to schedule
你知道，你的代码和你正在尝试安排日程。
your threats and you are trying to order
你的威胁和你试图命令
as a resource request so that all doesn't happen.
作为一个资源请求，以便避免发生这种情况。
So like in our examples of, you know, trains,
那么就像我们之前举的例子，你知道的，火车，
when you go south, east, west, and then north, south,
当你向南、东、西、然后北、南走时，
then you don't go first north, south,
然后你不先往北走，南走，
and then east, west.
然后向东，向西。
But they are related and yeah.
但是他们是有关系的，是的。
Okay, so many operating systems avoid the deadlock.
好的，所以很多操作系统避免死锁。
You know, they don't, you know, ignore the deadlock.
你知道，他们不会，你知道，忽视僵局。
When can you ignore the deadlock?
当可以忽略死锁时？
To let me, you know, here we are making a little bit of fun
让我告诉你，我们这里正在开一点小玩笑。
that, you know, denial in this Oistrich algorithm.
那个，你知道的，在这个鸵鸟算法中的否认。
So, you know, you pretend the problem is not,
所以，你知道，你假装问题不存在，
doesn't happen, is not happening.
不会发生，没有发生。
But when actually deadlock denial, it's okay.
但当实际上陷入僵局时，也没关系。
When crashing, freezing isn't that big of a problem, yes.
当崩溃时，冻结并不是一个很大的问题，是的。
And when they are very, very, happen very rarely.
而且当它们发生时，非常非常罕见。
When it happens very rarely, okay.
当它发生得非常罕见时，好的。
That's what, when it's okay.
那是什么，什么时候可以。
And if you were to push a deadlock, you know,
如果你要推动僵局，你知道的，
to do deadlock prevention or avoidance,
为了避免死锁，可以采取以下措施：
will require very expensive algorithms,
需要非常昂贵的算法，
will dramatically increase the complexity of the system.
这将极大地增加系统的复杂性。
Right?
对吗？
So preventing deadlocks, like I mentioned,
所以，像我之前提到的那样，预防死锁，
you have enough resources
你有足够的资源
so that no one ever runs out of resources, right?
所以没有人会耗尽资源，对吗？
But other things, every source can be shared,
但是其他的事情，每一个资源都可以被分享，
like the CPU.
喜欢中央处理器。
You have 100, you have one thread, fine.
你有100个，你有一个线程，好的。
You have 10 threads, fine.
你有10个线程，好的。
You have 1000 threads, fine.
你有1000个线程，好的。
Everyone will be slower,
每个人都会变得更慢，
but still you are going to get your share of the CPU.
但是你仍然会得到你应得的CPU份额。
And finally, like you don't allow waiting, right?
最后，你不喜欢等待，对吗？
And this is what happens in many cases, right?
是的，这在许多情况下都会发生，对吗？
When you call and the other part is not available
当你打电话时，对方不可用。
or when the system is overloaded,
或者当系统负载过重时，
you get a busy signal, right?
你会听到忙音，对吗？
Failure.
失败。
Try again.
再试一次。
The same in ethernet, in the networking.
在以太网中，网络中也是一样的。
There are a collision between the packets.
数据包之间发生了碰撞。
Try again.
再试一次。
Okay?
好的。
So it's again, it's inefficient.
所以，又是这样，效率低下。
And in some cases you cannot do it,
有些情况下你无法做到，
but it can be inefficient in some cases,
但在某些情况下可能效率低下，
but it's a very simple method.
但这是一个非常简单的方法。
So this is an example,
所以这是一个例子，
if you have infinite resources in our case
如果在我们的情况下你拥有无限的资源
in which the deadlock happened
发生僵局的情况下
because limited resources, no longer a problem.
由于资源有限，不再是一个问题。
Another way to, yeah.
另一种方式，是的。
Another way to do it is to prevent the deadlock
另一种方法是防止死锁发生。
is to require everything at the beginning.
是要求一切都在开始时完成。
Everyone requires everything at the beginning.
每个人在开始时都需要一切。
And therefore, you know,
所以，你知道的，
and you know exactly what everyone is using.
而且你清楚每个人都在使用什么。
So you can allocate from, at the beginning,
所以你可以从一开始就分配。
resources to everyone so that you make sure
给每个人提供资源，以确保你们都能使用。
there is no prevention, there is no deadlock.
没有预防措施，也没有僵局。
And then force all stress to request resources
然后强制所有压力请求资源
in particular order, like we discussed.
按照特定的顺序，就像我们讨论过的那样。
But here, you know, it's a very, very important thing
但是在这里，你知道，这是一件非常非常重要的事情。
is that one thing this happens
这是一件事情发生了吗？
when you acquire the locks X and Y and Y and X
当你获得锁X和Y以及Y和X时
is because these two operations of acquiring the two locks,
是因为获取这两个锁的两个操作，
they are not atomic.
它们不是原子的。
But what if the operation of acquiring these locks is atomic?
但是如果获取这些锁的操作是原子的呢？
Then everything will work, right?
那么一切都会正常工作，对吗？
Because only one of the threads will be successful.
因为只有一个线程会成功。
And the thread which is successful
和成功的线程
is going to run to completion,
将会运行到完成。
is going to release the two resources, two locks,
将要发布两个资源，两个锁。
and the other strand is going to come up and run.
另一根链条将会升起并运行。
And how do you do that?
你是如何做到的呢？
In practice?
实际上呢？
Well, use another lock to make sure
好的，使用另一个锁来确保
that acquiring the locks X and Y are atomic.
获取锁X和Y是原子操作的。
Okay?
好的。
So that's why I do it.
所以这就是我为什么这么做。
You can also do it, like I said earlier on,
你也可以做，就像我之前说的那样，
that by enforcing the order.
通过执行命令。
So in this case, if you both threads A and B
在这种情况下，如果你同时有A线程和B线程
acquire the same order, again, you are fine.
再次获得相同的订单，你没问题。
Does it matter in which order the locks are released?
释放锁的顺序是否重要？
No, because the release is not awaiting operation.
不，因为发布不需要等待操作。
Okay.
Sure, I can help you with that. Please go ahead and provide me with the text you would like me to translate.
So we are going to stop here
所以我们要停在这里。
and we are going to continue talking about deadlocks
我们将继续讨论死锁问题。
next lecture.
下一堂课。
Good luck with project one
祝你在项目一中好运。
and see you all virtually on a Saturday.
并在周六通过虚拟方式见到你们所有人。
Thank you.
谢谢你。
(upbeat music)
（欢快的音乐）
[ Silence ]
[沉默]